[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can one know that you're making progress in practice, if your practice is going right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it going wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's something related to what we spoke before, being self-transparent and authentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are self-transparent, and by that it's meant if you don't... if you don't lie to yourself, as in, if you don't try to
[SPEAKER_00]: Turn a blind eye to the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this case, in this case, the truth being, you are not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody starts as a puthujjana.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that, that should be your criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, whatever you're doing, in terms of the practice, it should be freeing you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least to a degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least to a degree that you can then start discerning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then use that criteria to keep doing that thing more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why it won't be so easy is because people are not self-transparent, because that's done for the purpose of protecting oneself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't acknowledge certain truths, you don't admit to yourself, you hold a view, you defend a stance point.
[SPEAKER_00]: All that is done so you don't expose yourself to that existential suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you remove that attitude, and then you're not suffering as a result of your practice, you can know that you are on a better way to free yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't remove that attitude, whatever you end up doing on the pretext of practice, it's going to be done as a form of cover-up very often.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can also ask yourself whether you're covering things up by, eh... see if you get upset by, eh... when you encounter other people's views.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're different than yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you take them personally, if you feel threatened by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are, means you're holding on to your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if happen... those views happen to be right that you have,
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that you're holding that means you're not right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very different than, like, expecting a a kind of feeling or a perceptual, like, light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I saw the blue light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that means I've reached stage one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I do next after the stage... the blue stage?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing like that in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm sure there's plenty of contemporary meditations being taught on those lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're meditating to get a blue light or whatever you want, by all means, but that's not freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Freedom from suffering lies only in one thing, and that thing is understanding the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma means phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma means knowledge of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: And knowledge not like a informational sort of collecting the data and like laying it all out in a psychological manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature of the arisen things, the things that have nature to manifest, what's their fundamental, universal nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understand that fully, you are free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't suffer because you can't appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that has nothing to do, even if you never see any special light or have special experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: As Sariputta said himself, he was the foremost after the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: According to the Buddha himself, he said, Sariputta is the foremost after me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... he... he said he couldn't even see a mere goblin, let alone have any other supernatural experience or... or release.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was all clarity of understanding and mindfulness and wisdom, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why he was the second after the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: While others who had, you know, fly in the air and glide... glide the sun and the moon and see the future lives and past lives and all, there's nothing to do with the freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, it can be a side effect of it for some, but it's completely irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose that's what people are looking for, a kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Novelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...external thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can show everybody... Well, because people's views are generally... they start by being fully embedded in their conceit and self-centeredness, vanity often, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you just judge that the new spiritual find, inspiration, you judge with those criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, what's unique, what's new, what's uncommon, what's lofty in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, very often, what can be kind of accessed quickly and be so pleasant, it fully overwhelms me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just extension of sensual craving, basically, directed elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, should you challenge yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to see where you're at in the practice, should you put challenges upon yourself, like ascetic practices?
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially if you have none.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your life is not... if your life is quite a comfortable, easy, no physical discomfort, anything like that, absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You use common sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't challenge yourself to the point of risking your life while you're still unenlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's supposed to say you would wisely avoid a wild elephant, a mad cow, a raging dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean he would go and climb on top of a palace and live sheltered and hidden for the rest of his life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think, yeah, I think we addressed it before probably, but as it is the case with most people today, on average, certainly in Europe and America, on average people are soft.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like even those who are kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Not as wealthy, has to have to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still have relatively comfortable lives in comparison to how it used to be back in the day in India.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so that's something you have to factor in.
[SPEAKER_00]: The threshold from which you begin.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one of those things that you could challenge yourself with is solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that is a challenge and that is also a necessity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people actually congregate and come together and live together and pair up, put up with all sorts of discomforts, because solitude is far more terrifying than anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something your practice should be going towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would say, you develop the recognition of pleasure in solitude, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You learn how to find solitude valuable and pleasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only learn that through discernment, through understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you see the benefits of it, and that's how you see the dangers when the solitude is absent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you develop a value, factual value of solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how can a layperson do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it really depends how far that layperson wants to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they're thinking about, you know, practicing towards arahantship, anāgāmī, yeah, you can't be a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, theoretically, you can be an anāgāmī's layperson, but there was... Or live like a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or live like a layperson, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can live like a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can do that, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Even back in the Buddha's time, that was... that was not common.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, people would go forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, today, it's kind of virtually impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to go that far, you would have to give up the... the way of a householder's life.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can... you don't necessarily have to go and become a monk, but you have to live like a renunciate, like somebody who's practicing restraint, lives a celibate life,
[SPEAKER_00]: Secluded from people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just secluded by not engaging with them, but living with them, but actually physically, physically removed from people.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly for the periods of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, so you have to recognize that if you don't want to leave the life of a layman that you know, then you have to sort of lower down your expectations in terms of how much you can develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's a lot of people are alone in the city.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're not alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being, being, like, living alone doesn't mean you're actually alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no sign of solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need, you need that, that, that physical distance, at least initially, to discern, exactly, to discern the sign of solitude, to discern, well, the sign of your own mind, in a way, the framework of others as a phenomenon, all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, jhāna, any sort of establishment of mind you need, you can't just sit in a hall with thirty other people on a retreat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're all perfectly silent, you are with others.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are others.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that... well, it affects the outlook of your experience at the time when you're present.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you remove yourself from it, then you get to understand the framework of that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yes, you can theoretically be with others and not be affected by that on that existential level.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, we all start with a mistake of ignorance, with a mistake of a vijā that is beginningless and real as such, which means you have to reverse to a degree in order to get to see the nature of things and then you can go back to some of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you still wouldn't be able to live as a layman, somebody who has understood it properly, freed himself from sensuality, became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, if you recognize the limitations that you are not willing to give up, as in you don't want to go and become a monk and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you just have to, like, measure what you can do in that setup and try and tailor your lay setup.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have to work five days a week, well, the other two days, I don't know, rent a cabin in the middle of the forest and that's where you spend it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't spend the valuable time that you can have in solitude, just socializing with others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Spend it in seclusion, study, if you still need to clarify what you need to do,
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's different kinds of solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a physical seclusion, mental seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Oh, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need physical seclusion, because the mental seclusion is... That's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to develop a proper mental seclusion, that can only be done through physical seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yes, like again, as a lay... if a lay person is not able to have a complete physical seclusion, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you do the best out of what you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a sense, if you can't be physically remote from people, well, at least spend your time not engaging with them, if you don't have to engage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't talk to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have to talk, well, then talk the bare minimum.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's difficult, because it's a form of engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not talking to the person that's sitting right next to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already affected just by being with others.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if there is a public agreement between us, that we will not speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still others, presence of others, the assumption of the external point of view to yourself, all that is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just... you do have to be physically removed, some people more, some people less, for periods of time, to develop certain clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, just pick a suited random, and it is an 80% chance you'll be talking about value of solitude, and forest, remote dwellings, and empty lodgings, and go there, and, you know, don't waste your time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like one of the reasons why a layperson cannot develop these things, it's because the household life is crowded and dusty.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's crowded, it's always people, always people, always things going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't practice them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, you must abandon that type of life if you want to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, again, even if you don't want to go and become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the lifestyle choices matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not change any aspect of your lifestyle and expect to develop practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the precepts are already a lifestyle choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in terms of looking after yourself, I mean, physical health, what's what's going too far?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's not going far enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what's going too far?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, are we supposed to eat... eat just the bare minimum, just so they can get the... just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you keep on breathing, keep on walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're eating very little, obviously, you start to waste away.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's... there is no chance a person in that kind of state, going on pīndapāta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a mountainous area.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, like, especially for the monks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if they want to live like forest monks, or just in name, but actually in life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seclusion means far away from other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion means effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion means exposure to elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion means ability to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion means toughness, physical toughness, discomfort, that doesn't bother you, that you find comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, again, as I said,
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimately, if a person manages to properly develop their mind, properly establish their mind in jhāna and in similar establishments, they will enjoy the roughness, toughness, discomfort even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to get there, they already need to be able to take a degree of pain without their mind just melting away, without their mindfulness fizzling out the moment that discomfort touches them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is usually why people are afraid.
[SPEAKER_00]: People
[SPEAKER_00]: And I, again, I speak out of personal experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you get into some meditation, then immediately, oh, I must stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything, basically, that will result in fatigue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that will tire me, it will compromise my mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or make me sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or make me sick, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Health, it's the whole... it's the principle that you sort of open this up with.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the... like when the Buddha said, you can't stop eating because you will die, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: What you do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't blame food for your sensuality, because you weren't there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, there are certain things you have to stop doing, such as sexual intercourse, killing others, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That cannot be done wholesomely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But things that are necessary, or things that are helpful, can be determined helpful, whether they are rooted in wholesome intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're mindful, if you develop discernment, and if you invest effort in clarity of your motivation in regard to the reasons why you're eating food,
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha himself said, sometimes he would eat two bowls of food filled to the brim, while he has disciples who live only on a handful of rice every third day or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean the Buddha was sensual.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means that at that time, there was a need for more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, even if he ate ten bowls of food, for no point in that duration of that action of eating would have he been rooted in sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or in vanity, or desire for physical beauty, so he eats, so he can be healthy and admired by others.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He ate because he was hungry.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that takes... that takes proper mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you are careless, then you're automatically eating out of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's same with health.
[SPEAKER_00]: People get obsessed with their health and with their... whatever... tablets and multivitamins and acupunctures and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can help when there is a need for that help.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more often than not, people start protecting it just for the sake of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But health is very much like the immune system.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll develop it if you challenge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't, you lose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not accidental when you hear like, oh, the old monk in Thailand, 90-something years, walking Pindapar every single day of his life, like four or five kilometers, and lived to the old age fully active.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because he built
[SPEAKER_00]: He built, basically, his body adjusted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resilience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through the exposure, through through fatigue, effort, strength, endurance, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, if your life doesn't require that, you don't have to do it specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, it would probably be useful to have some sort of physical discipline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that will tire you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that will make you, make you, make your heart race, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't mean like do spiritual sort of energy flows with your tai chi or some yoga twists and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want actually to tire yourself to be able to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you be mindful, whether you're tired or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can your mindfulness remain unaffected by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if your mindfulness... and again, I'm speaking that our personal experience is a labor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I was afraid to get tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: I stopped doing sports, stopped exercising, because it would disturb my mindfulness, which is because I didn't know what mindfulness was.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that which I thought was mindfulness, was indeed disturbed by fatigue, by tiredness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I must stop that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was a complete mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wish somebody told me sooner.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fortunately, like, I didn't end up hurting myself, in terms of physically, as many monks do.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you stop everything, you just sit for a whole day, you don't do anything, and then suddenly, you forget how unfit you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go for a massive, long, too long or something, and you dislocate your... your disc slips and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that happens when... when body is just weak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... you lost a certain degree of resilience and strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you forgot about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go lift a box and that's it, because you've been doing... Yeah, you move a pot plant and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up with a chiropractor.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many times that happened to people?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, yeah, loads, loads.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all because, just because of that kind of same attitude of, I must not get tired, because it will disturb my mindfulness, and then becomes a habit of not getting tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want something that will tire you, so that you can see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if your mindfulness is disturbed by the mere fatigue, what are you going to do?
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're facing death, illness, dying of cancer, body shutting down, hurting from every angle, no way to rest from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, think how the monks lived back in the Buddha's day, in the edges of Himalayas, like, trekking for for months at end, just to meet the Buddha in time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, try.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, today, if you want to do that, you need, like, military training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take an average guy or you need to be doing that like gradually increasing for like decades to be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to recognize this necessity and also indifference towards mindfulness, whether you're fatigued or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're properly mindful, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it won't matter whether you're in a deathbed, struggling to breathe or you're perfectly healthy in full strength and full whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you discern where the mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, if you blame your fatigue, if you blame things you have to do, if you blame work, if you blame exercise, well, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can sort of survive like that, if you live in a precious environment, that's usually based on luxury and comfort, even if you don't necessarily recognize it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in, you know, in Sābhāsana Sutta, there's a whole, the Buddha said, there's a whole domain of asavas to be abandoned simply by enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring heat, cold, discomfort, tired, hunger, enduring insects, enduring elements, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're not able to endure it, if your mind folds away from it, just as a prospect of enduring, you're nowhere near it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't mean, of course, that people who live, like lay people who live in the cities, oh, I must go and run and live in a mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do need some sort of physical discipline, something that will challenge you and tire you and make you tougher and stronger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing too complicated, is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you want to have it rooted in those reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, sure, yeah, people can be doing exercise for all sorts of reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: For vanity, for wanting to be the best, the quickest, the strongest... That's the number one reason to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's... that's why often people will project, they will think, like, you can't do it for any other reason except the vanity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then... and they also equally mistakenly project, thinking, in order then to do something that won't be in vanity, it must be something completely different.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they get doing, like, Tai Chi or things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, again, it's a valid form of exercise for some, but it's not the one you're looking after.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to make you tougher or more resilient.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to look at things that actually are most economical.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the least effort, you get most result, in terms of your exercise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to spend five hours training and running and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do the minimum, as a form of discipline, as a form of chore,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it will pertain to everything else in a positive manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose a lot of the type of work that people used to do, generally, is more physical, you know, farm work and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not done out of, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's done out of necessity.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a side effect of that necessity was they were fit and tough and able to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now you have, like, gyms in the cities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is basically set up a luxury.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's all about mirrors and vanity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was just thinking that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, like, it's not denying the lifestyle has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't just go and start plowing the land and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is absolutely no need for that anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you recognize, like, certain loss with that, which is that, like, physical toughness, unable to endure discomfort and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you want to compensate for that, you don't have to change your lifestyle to a great degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: But exactly, you find, you do the training, you do the exercises, they will add up to that which you don't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And especially, as a monk who is interested to live like a forest monk,
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is interested to live solely on Pindaparth in the remote dwellings, frequenting the forest and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, we had that here happens, like when people were like 15 years younger than us, came and stayed here for a couple of days.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the third day, they were dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were broken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just having to walk five kilometers for their food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like done every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Almost look forward for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even, even the old ladies who live nearby... My goodness, yeah, yeah, the tea-picking ladies, yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The tea-picking... Yeah, 70-year-old, just held steep like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, probably 15 kilos of tea leaves in the bag on her back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he's there like a, like a mountain deer, just not a slip, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: She's been doing it her whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody who hasn't been doing it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody who hasn't been doing it, in order to do it, more often than not, it's like vanity is the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in a way, that's fine, if that's what makes you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you just change the reason and keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for somebody who lives in the city, if you want to go and start, I don't know, endurance training or strength training, go to a gym that doesn't have the mirrors.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no reason for lifting in front of a mirror, except vanity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even actually, even in terms of the form, and developing the proper lifting form, for example, in strength training, you should not look in the mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the... the... what was that?
[SPEAKER_00]: The Russian Olympic team.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, maybe they still do it, but back in the day, they used to lift this complex, like Olympic snatches, and power cleans, and so on, blindfolded.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you want to learn the motorics, you want to learn the movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the compound exercises, no mirror, strength, endurance, repetition, and increasing the weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to look... if you want to develop a muscle bulging out, so that you'd be attracting... You cannot do that for wholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you being fit is a result of your discipline and basically pursuit of physical toughness and endurance, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense as you being healthy as a result of eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just don't... because you can't slip into unwholesome accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't accidentally
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, start eating for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do it by deciding to go for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't accidentally go and start training with weights and accidentally do bodybuilding.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bodybuilding is all about, basically, developing proportions, developing size, which means it's all about the way you look, which means it's all about the vanity.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you don't do any form of that, if you actually... if you actually do the strength endurance training, then you wouldn't need more than what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Half an hour, three times a week, using some proper strength, like routines, proven, been around for like 40 years, and you wouldn't have to spend like six hours jogging and running and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that you'll be healthy, you'll also be able to take the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't shy away from discomfort, you wouldn't shy away from physical fatigue, and nor would your mental composure be affected by it, because you trained yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, or just take a backpack, go in the mountains, and walk, and live in a tent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll get used to it, and you get tougher, you get stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, back in the day, the olden days... Yeah, but back in the day, like, there's no, it's not, it's, it's not accidental that the Buddha kept referring to, like, you know, living, like, trying to inspire monks with, like, similes of warriors, and, and soldiers, and toughness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it was like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine just
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, carrying a backpack of 5 kilos, let alone 15 or 20 kilos, and then hike for 20 kilometers on uneven terrain, that's a military training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Today, that's considered almost like, what, a military elite infantry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that was your lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't even get to sleep in a nice place, you get to sleep under a root of a tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean, like, people might not think they live a luxurious life,
[SPEAKER_00]: But in comparison, it's very... Like, even here on the hill, where we do walk Pindapur every single day, five to six kilometers, up and down the mountain, rain, wind, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overall, it's actually quite comfortable up here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's quite easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you do want to have the ultimate perspective in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did the root of a tree-dweller live?
[SPEAKER_00]: You think when they walked across the entire Bihar to meet the Buddha, they were just flying in the air.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, they're walking, carrying, carrying the ball, which were probably heavy cast iron ball, and you think a weak person can do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Kettles, pots.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kettles, pots, umbrellas, thick felt, those felt blankets they used to use in India for rain and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like 15, 20 kilo of weight on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sun, heat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, they did not have.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was the name of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Baba, Baba tent.
[SPEAKER_00]: A thousand pounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, a thousand pounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: 800 gram tent or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are massive wall blankets, canvases, bowls and...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just just picture that and picture that doing... you doing that every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on top of that, that's your practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, that's how you also practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are a bit too precious, in a sense, including myself, where I started.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think, oh, I stole this, nothing must challenge me, because this is... Yeah, you start like that, but you have to see that that's not where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is not in your exercise, the problem is not in your eating, taking medicine, paying attention to your health.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is you doing those things for wrong reasons, which means it's your reasons that make it a problem or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same sense, as I was just saying, if you want to go and develop solitude, you have to be able to take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will often require, yeah, the degree of physical discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Independence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Independence, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting wood, chopping wood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't have, like, twenty servants, twenty junior monk servants around you, just, just attending to your every wish.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want solitude, you have to do it yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you have to be able to do it yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't be able if your body is simply not strong enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't, you can't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just can't take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't get out of bed after one day's work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that sense, exercise can start approximating that for those who don't work like that, who don't have that toughness developed through work and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, good cardio.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, get your heart pumping, whether through lifting weights or whether through running, if you can, even treadmills and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, don't get obsessed about it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do a research, see which one is the most economical.
[SPEAKER_00]: By that I mean, the least you can do, the most you get from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, I think there's a universal consensus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of those who know, of those who don't identify weights with bodybuilding, who know the difference, of like professional athletes, it's like, you know, heavy barbell training, kettlebells, bodyweight, pull-ups and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that will, you know, increase your bone densities, joint strength, stability, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can do your tai chi if you want in the spare time, but you actually want to stress the body in a controlled manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it gets tougher, stronger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you can eat one meal a day, and go and climb the mountain, and carry a 20 kilo backpack, and sleep on a rock, like a baby.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know, you know that difference even, you know, out of like our own experience, when you, when you, you live in Europe, or some well sort of well-developed
[SPEAKER_00]: Temple.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know, you like even going to Thailand and staying in some more rural temples, coming to Sri Lanka.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it's just that, yeah, people who were not prepared physically, well, they didn't last long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, those who did, had to go through a lot of pain very quickly, because they just haven't been ready for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And above all, people end up feeling it, feeling the prospect
[SPEAKER_00]: Our physical discomfort, challenge, endurance, fatigue, even without actually engaging in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, that's something we've seen many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially in the monasteries, they were about work, lots of work and war projects.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people had to work, you just see the genuine, genuine terror in their eyes, because it's just going to be overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mindfulness is going to go, and they'll think about sensuality, and then they might disrobe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that should worry you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the fact that you might have to work, or get tired, or exercise.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that doing that will push you all the way back into sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can avoid it initially, until you start developing yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you never make the effort to develop yourself in the right manner, you can't avoid it forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, once your health starts to fail, strength is relative.
[SPEAKER_00]: For an old person, body failing, what used to be weakness, it is now strength, in comparison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, lifestyle choices matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take your health for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take your strength for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't take your freedom from illness for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, start emulating and preparing yourself for when those things go, for when those things start challenging you physically, which will then challenge you mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can take it, then you can take your mind even further above it, and really not be affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as the Buddha said, again, in Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam, there's a whole set of taints, a whole set of asuras,
[SPEAKER_00]: To be abandoned purely by enduring, by toughing them out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's something that's often missing today.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are way too spiritual, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even their exercise becomes spiritual.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't actually pertain to the physical aspect anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Certainly lifestyles become too spiritual.
[SPEAKER_00]: No manual labor, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you pay attention to the... if you're interested in practice, you pay attention to the lifestyle choices, the choices you make, not just for today and tomorrow, but in the long run as well, and factor that in.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're interested in practice and developing the environment that will support your solitude and so on, pay attention to preparing your body physically to be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy to keep the vanity out, if you're careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Avoid looking yourself in the mirror,
[SPEAKER_00]: Do the compound lifts or general type of exercises.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will stress your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily result in some developing of proportions and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do need to start stressing yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, in the same manner, you can't expect to just jump into solitude from a busy life.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can be forced into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can allow yourself to be forced into it, which is usually how those popular going-to-retreats work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you get all these real energy releases and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's because of your lifestyle beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't go for that, you want to start exposing yourself to that type of stress, gradually, but pretty much steadily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not optional, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize what the goal is, which is to be able to find joy and happiness,
[SPEAKER_00]: And to prefer the actual physical solitude and absence of other people, and then to develop yourself for that, physically and mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how mentally do you stress your mind, mentally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by being alone, deciding to be alone, and not engaging in any distraction, not answering any phone calls, don't going to see anyone, for the periods of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: No distraction, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, as I said, if you are relatively fit, physically, can take some pain and toughness, yeah, take a backpack and go for like three or four day hike in a little tent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will give you a sense of how you used to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And practice in that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just endure and put up with elements, but actually take your mind above it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In terms of, like, just having a minor headache, you know, little headache, instant pain killer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instant relief seeked immediately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you just don't take the pain killer... Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize what... how you want to live and take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you can take medicine when you're ill, for sake of staying healthy, not out of fear for getting sick.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you will eat,
[SPEAKER_00]: For the sake of staying alive and healthy, not for beautification or fear of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You took responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you'll exercise, in order to be able to take the pain even more, without being afraid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just to deal with the simple dwelling, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Taking you away from the elements, but not overly protecting you from...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you need a thick soft mattress?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the body is not used to sleep on hard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it not used to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you never exposed it to.
[SPEAKER_00]: You never stressed it in a manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not, it's not empty ascetic practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's empty or not, it's whether you don't do it for the right reasons or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the utmost, most inspiring ascetic performance can be more empty than eating and exercising, if you do it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you do eating and exercising for the right reasons, the reasons that you understand, the reasons that will pertain to your freedom from suffering, through your effort, yeah, that's what makes it wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're just going self-mortifying yourself for just the reason of whatever,
[SPEAKER_00]: Proving to yourself that you do it, crushing it, or whatever, without any grain of reflection or insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, in that sense, it's completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eh... being, eh... skin and bones means I'm on the right path.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there were... there were that suttas as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: The, eh... that, eh... King...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it's Pasenadi or the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anyway, he went to visit the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was staying in this kuti, and on the way to the kuti, he was walking to that park.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all these young and healthy monks were doing walk meditation, like pacing from one tree to the other, back and forth, and they were quite happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, wow, look at that!
[SPEAKER_00]: This teaching is so wonderful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he praised the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha said, what you see, praise the word in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, well, for example, just now, this teaching is so wonderful when you have like men in their youth, still fully able to access sensual pleasures, enjoy life, carry it all up, and they're happy about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're very content.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you go to the other ascetics and brāhmaṇas, they're all dried up, skin and bone, just hating on everyone, miserable, unhappy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to start discerning the reasons behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether that's those actions are aimed at health, life, strength, lifestyle in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are responsible for making them wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: necessarily determined by themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very few are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like non-celibacy, of course, that's always unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Killing, harming, lying, stealing, that's always unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: But pretty much everything else, it's going to be unwholesome if you do it for unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if everybody else thinks it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's wholesome to sit in a dhamma hall with 50 people, in silence, that's that's noble and beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Often it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people end up doing it because they're still afraid to be alone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they need support for their practice, which is supposed to develop them as an individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop as an individual by needing others.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't work like that.